I hope you'll understand my English.
آمل في أن تفهموا لغتي الإنجليزية.
In the mornings it is terrible, and the afternoon is worst.
إنها في الصباح عسيرة، وبعد الظهر أسوأ.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
During many years, I made some speeches starting with this
خلال عدة سنوات، قمت بإلقاء بعض الخطابات تبدأ بهذا
saying: "City is not a problem, it's a solution."
المثل: "المدينة ليست مشكلة، إنها حل."
And more and more, I'm convinced that
وأكثر وأكثر، أنا مقتنع بأنها
it's not only a solution for a country,
ليست حل للدولة فحسب،
but it's a solution for the problem of climate change.
بل أيضا أنها حل لمشكلة تغير المناخ.
But we have a very pessimistic approach about the cities.
لكن لدينا نهج متشائم جدا نحو المدن.
I'm working in cities for almost 40 years,
أعمل في مجال المدن حوالي 40 عاما تقريبا،
and where every mayor is trying to tell me his city is so big,
حيث كل عُمدة مدينة يحاول أن يخبرني، أوه، مدينته كبيرة جدا.
or the other mayors say, "We don't have financial resources,"
و العُمد الآخرون يقولون، ليس لدينا موارد مالية.
I would like to say
أود أن أقول،
from the experience I had: every city in the world
من خبرتي التي إكتسبتها، كل مدينة في العالم
can be improved in less than three years.
يمكن أن تتطور في أقل من ثلاث سنوات.
There's no matter of scale. It's not a question of scale,
بغض النظر عن المستوى، أنه ليس سؤلا عن المستوى،
it's not a question of financial resources.
أنه ليس سؤلا عن الموارد المالية.
Every problem in a city has to have its own equation of co-responsibility
كل مشكلة في المدينة يجب أن يكون لها المعادلة الخاصة بها من المسؤولية المشتركة.
and also a design.
وأيضا التصميم.
So to start, I want to introduce some characters
ولنبدأ، أريد أن أعرض بعض السمات
from a book I made for teenagers.
من كتاب كتبته للشباب اليافعين.
The best example of quality of life is the turtle
أفضل مثال لنوعية الحياة هو السلحفاة،
because the turtle is an example of living and working together.
لأن السلحفاة هي مثال للعيش والعمل معاً.
And when you realize that the casque of the turtle
وعندما تدرك أن نتوء (غطاء) السلحفاة،
looks like an urban tessitura,
يشبه جزءا أساسيا من المجموعة الحضرية السائدة،
and can we imagine, if we cut the casque of the turtle, how sad she's going to be?
ويمكن التصور لو قطعنا النتوء(غطاء) السلحفاة، كيف سيُحزنها ذلك؟
And that's what we're doing in our cities:
وذلك ما سنقوم به في المدن!
living here, working here, having leisure here.
السكن هنا، العمل هنا، الترفيه هنا.
And most of the people are leaving the city
ومعظم السكان يغادرون المدينة،
and living outside of the city.
ويسكنون خارج المدينة.
So, the other character is Otto, the automobile.
لذا، السمة الأخرى هي (أوتو)، السيارة.
He is invited for a party -- he never wants to leave.
لقد تمت دعوتها لحفل. وهي لا تريد أن تغادر أبداً.
The chairs are on the tables and still drinking,
الكراسي على الطاولات و تزال تشرب،
and he drinks a lot. (Laughter)
وشربت كثيرا. (ضحك)
And he coughs a lot. Very egotistical:
وسعلت كثيراً. أنانية جداً.
he carries only one or two people
تحمل واحد أو اثنين فقط من الناس.
and he asks always for more infrastructure.
وهي دائما تتسأل عن المزيد من البنية التحتية.
Freeways.
الطرق السريعة.
He's a very demanding person.
إنها كشخص لحوح جداً.
And on the other hand, Accordion, the friendly bus,
لهذا -- وعلى الجانب الأخر، الأكورديون، الحافلة الصديقة،
he carries 300 people --
تحمل 300 شخصاً،
275 in Sweden; 300 Brazilians. (Laughter)
275 في السويد، 300 برازيلي.(ضحك)
Speaking about the design: every city has its own design.
الحديث عن التصميم، كل مدينة لديها تصميمها الخاص.
Curitiba, my city: three million in the metropolitan area,
"كوريتيبا"، مدينتي، يسكن ثلاثة ملايين نسمة في منطقة العاصمة،
1,800,000 people in the city itself.
1,800,000 نسمة في المدينة نفسها.
Curitiba, Rio: it's like two birds kissing themselves.
"كوريتيبا"، ريو: إنهما مثل طائران يقبلان أنفسهما.
Oaxaca, San Francisco -- it's very easy:
أواكساكا، سان فرانسيسكو -- إنها بسيطة جداً.
Market Street, Van Ness and the waterfront.
شارع السوق، فان نيس، والواجهة البحرية.
And every city has its own design.
وكل مدينة لديها تصميمها الخاص.
But to make it happen, sometimes you have to propose a scenario
لكن لتجعلها تحدث أحيانا، يجب عليك أن تقترح سيناريو.
and to propose a design --
وتقترح تصميم،
an idea that everyone, or the large majority,
فكرة يمكن لأي شخص، أو الغالبية العظمى،
will help you to make it happen.
أن تساعدك في تنفيذها على أرض الواقع.
And that's the structure of the city of Curitiba.
وذلك هو أساس مدينة "كوريتيبا".
And it's an example of living and working together.
وإنه مثال للسكن والعمل معاً.
And this is where we have more density;
وهذا هو المكان الذي لدينا فيه كثافة أكثر;
it's where we have more public transport.
أنه المكان الذي لدينا فيه الكثير من وسائل النقل العامة.
So, this system started in '74. We started with 25,000 passengers a day,
وبدأ هذا النظام في عام 74. لقد بدأنا بـ 25,000 راكب في اليوم،
now it's 2,200,000 passengers a day.
الآن بلغ عدد الركاب 2,200,000 في اليوم.
And it took 25 years until another city ...
و أخذ 25 عاما في مدينة أخرى،
which is Bogota, and they did a very good job.
وهي بوغوتا، وقاموا بعمل جيد.
And now there's 83 cities all over the world that they
والآن هناك حوالي 83 مدينة في مختلف أنحاء العالم والتي تقوم
are doing what they call the BRT of Curitiba.
بعمل ما يعرف ب "حافلة النقل السريع" في مدينة "كوريتيبا".
And one thing: it's important not for only your own city;
وشيء واحد: أنه مهم، ليس فقط لمدينتك.
every city, besides its normal problems,
كل مدينة، إلى جانب مشاكلها الطبيعية،
they have a very important role
لديها دور -- دور هام جدا --
in being with the whole humanity.
في أن تتماشى مع البشرية جمعاء.
That means mostly two main issues --
وذلك يعني في الغالب مسألتين رئيسيتين هما،
mobility and sustainability -- are becoming very important for the cities.
التنقل والاستدامة، أصبحت مهمة جدا بالنسبة للمدن
And this is an articulated bus, double-articulated.
وهذا هو حافلة الأكورديون. الأكورديون المزدوج.
And we are very close to my house.
ونحن بالقرب من منزلي.
You can come when you are in Curitiba and have a coffee there.
يمكنك الدخول عندما تكون في كوريتيبا وتناول القهوة هناك.
And that's the evolution of the system.
وذلك هو تطور النظام.
What in the design that made the difference
ماذا في التصميم الذي صنع الفرق
is the boarding tubes:
أهي أنابيب الصعود.
the boarding tube gives to the bus the same performance as a subway.
أنبوب الصعود يعطي الحافلة نفس الأداء كما في مترو الأنفاق.
That's why, I'm trying to say,
هذا هو السبب، أحاول أن أقول،
it's like metro-nizing the bus.
أنها حافلة مثل المترو الدائري.
This is the design of the bus,
وهذا هو تصميم الحافلة.
and you can pay before entering the bus you're boarding.
ويمكنك دفع الأجرة قبل دخولك إلى الحافلة التي ستصعدها.
And for handicapped, they can use this as a normal system.
وبالنسبة للمعاقين، يمكنهم استخدام هذا كنظام عادي.
What I'm trying to say is
لكن ما أريد أن أقوله، هو
the major contribution on carbon emissions are from the cars --
أن المساهمة الرئيسية في إنبعاثات الكربون هي من السيارات.
more than 50 percent -- so when we depend only on cars, it's ...
أكثر من 50%. لذا عندما نعتمد على السيارات، إنها
-- that's why when we're talking about sustainability,
-- هذا هو السبب عندما نتحدث عن الإستدامة،
it's not enough, green buildings.
إنه لا يكفي، المباني الخضراء.
It's not enough, a new materials.
إنه لا يكفي، المواد الجديدة.
It's not enough, new sources of energy.
إنه لا يكفي، مصادر جديدة للطاقة.
It's the concept of the city, the design of the city,
إنه مفهوم المدينة. تصميم المدينة.
that's also important, too. And also, how to teach the children.
وهو أيضا مهم جدا -- وأيضا، كيفية تدريس الأطفال.
I'll speak on this later on.
سأتحدث عن هذا لا حقاً.
Our idea of mobility is trying
إن فكرتنا من التنقل هي محاولة
to make the connections between all the systems.
لوضع روابط بين جميع الأنظمة.
We started in '83, proposing for the city of Rio
لقد بدأنا في عام 83، باقتراح لمدينة ريو دي جانيرو
how to connect the subway with the bus.
عن كيفية ربط مترو الأنفاق بحافلة الركاب.
The subway was against, of course.
كان مترو الأنفاق مناهضا للفكرة، بالطبع.
And 23 years after, they called us to develop -- we're developing this idea.
وبعد 23 عاما، اتصلوا بنا لتطويره -- قمنا بتطوير هذه الفكرة.
And you can understand how different it's going to be,
ويمكنك أن تفهم كيف ستكون مختلفة،
the image of Rio with the system --
صورة ريو دي جانيرو بهذا النظام --
one-minute frequency.
تردد دقيقة واحدة.
And it's not Shanghai,
إنها ليست مدينة شنغاهاي،
it's not being colored during the day, only at night
إنها لن تكون ملونة خلال النهار، إلا في الليل.
it will look this way.
سيكون منظرها بهذه الطريقة.
And before you say it's a Norman Foster design,
وقبل أن نقول إنه تصميم "نورمان فوستر"،
we designed this in '83.
قمنا بهذا التصميم في عام 83.
And this is the model,
وهذا هو النموذج،
how it's going to work. So, it's the same system;
كيف سيعمل. ولذلك انه نفس النظام;
the vehicle is different. And that's the model.
المركبة مختلفة. وذلك هو النموذج.
What I'm trying to say is, I'm not trying
ما أريد أن أقوله هو، أنني لا أحاول
to prove which system of transport is better.
أن أثبت أي نظام للتنقل هو الأفضل.
I'm trying to say we have to combine
أريد أن اقول بأنه يجب علينا الجمع بين الأنظمة.
all the systems, and with one condition:
للجمع بيم جميع الأنظمة، وبشرط واحد:
never -- if you have a subway, if you have surface systems,
أبداً -- إذا كان لديك مترو أنفاق، إذا كان لديك أنظمة على السطح،
if you have any kind of system --
إذا كان لديك أي نوع من النظام --
never compete in the same space.
لا تنافس مطلقا في نفس الحيز.
And coming back to the car, I always used to say
وبالعودة إلى السيارة، كنت دائما أقول
that the car is like your mother-in-law:
أن السيارة هي مثل حماتك (أم زوجتك).
you have to have good relationship with her,
يجب أن تكون لديك علاقة جيدة معها،
but she cannot command your life.
لكنها لا تسطيع قيادة حياتك.
So, when the only woman in your life is your mother-in-law,
لذا عندما تكون المرأة الوحيدة في حياتك هي حماتك،
you have a problem. (Laughter)
يكون لديك مشلكة. (ضحك)
So, all the ideas about how to transform through design --
لهذا جميع الأفكار عن كيفية التحول من خلال التصميم --
old quarries and open universities and botanic garden --
المحاجر القديمة، والجامعات المفتوحة، والحدائق النباتية --
all of it's related to how we teach the children.
وجميع ما يتعلق بكيفية تعليمنا للأطفال.
And the children, we teach during six months how to separate their garbage.
و نقوم بتعليم الأطفال خلال ستة أشهر كيفية فرز وفصل قماماتهم.
And after, the children teach their parents.
وبعد، الأطفال، سيقومون بتعليم والديهم.
And now we have 70 percent --
و الآن لدينا 70% --
since 20 years, it's the highest rate of separation of garbage in the world.
منذ 20 عاما، أنه أعلى معدل لفصل وفرز القمامة في العالم.
Seven zero.
سبعة - صفر.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So teach the children.
لهذا علم الأطفال.
I would like to say, if we want to have a sustainable world
أريد أن أقول، إذا أردنا أن يكون لدينا عالم مستادم،
we have to work with everything what's said,
يجب علينا العمل بكل شيء ما ذكر.
but don't forget the cities and the children.
لكن لا تنسى المدن والأطفال.
I'm working in a museum and also a multi-use city,
وأعمل في المتحف، وأيضا مدينة متعددة الإستخدام،
because you cannot have empty places during 18 hours a day.
لأنه لا يمكنك الحصول على أماكن فارغة خلال 18 ساعة في اليوم.
You should have always
يجب أن يكون لديك دائما
a structure of living and working together.
بنية للسكن والعمل معاً.
Try to understand the sectors in the city
حاول أن تفهم القطاعات في المدينة
that could play different roles during the 24 hours.
التي يمكن أن تلعب أدوارا مختلفة خلال ال 24 ساعة.
Another issue is, a city's like our family portrait.
مسألة أخرى هي، المدينة مثل صورة عائلتنا.
We don't rip our family portrait,
نحن لا نمزق صورة عائلتنا،
even if we don't like the nose of our uncle,
حتى ولو لم تعجبنا صورة أنف عمنا،
because this portrait is you.
لأن هذه الصورة هي أنت.
And these are the references that we have in any city.
وهذه هي الإشارات التي لدينا في أي مدينة.
This is the main pedestrian mall;
هذا هو مركز المشأة الرئيسي;
we did it in 72 hours. Yes, you have to be fast.
قمنا بعمله في 72 ساعة. نعم، يجب أن تكون سريعاً.
And these are the references from our ethnic contribution.
وهذه هي إشارات من مساهماتنا العرقية.
This is the Italian portal,
هذا هو المدخل الإيطالي،
the Ukrainian park, the Polish park, the Japanese square, the German park.
المنتزه الأوكراني، المنتزه البولندي، الساحة اليابانية، والمنتزه الألماني.
All of a sudden, the Soviet Union, they split.
جميع تقسيمات الإتحاد السوفيتي التي ظهرت فجأة.
And since we have people from
وحيث لدينا ناس من
Uzbekistan, Kazakhstan, Tajikistan, [unclear],
أوزباكستان، كازاخستان، طاجاكستان،
we have to stop the program.
يجب أن نوقف البرامج.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Don't forget: creativity starts when you cut a zero from your budget.
لا تنسى: الإبداع، إنه يبدأ عندما تخصم صفرا من ميزانيتك.
If you cut two zeros, it's much better.
إذا خصمت صفرين، فأنه أفضل بكثير.
And this is the Wire Opera theater. We did it in two months.
وهذا هو مسرح أوبرا واير(Wire Opera). لقد بتشييده خلال شهرين.
Parks -- old quarries that they were transformed into parks.
المنتزهات -- المحاجر القديمة التي تحولت إلى منتزهات.
Quarries once made the nature, and
المحاجر، صناعة مجردة للطبيعة،
sometimes we took this and we transformed.
أحيانا نأخذ هذا ونحوله.
And every part can be transformed;
كل جزء يمكن أن يتحول --
every frog can be transformed in a prince.
كل ضفدع يمكن أن يتحول إلى أمير.
So, in a city, you have to work fast.
لذا في المدينة، يجب أن تعمل بسرعة.
Planning takes time. And I'm proposing urban acupuncture.
التخطيط يستغرق وقتا. وأقترح الوخز بالإبر في المناطق الحضرية.
That means me, with some focal ideas to help the normal process of planning.
وهذا يعني لي، مع بعض الأفكار المحورية لمساعدة المعالجة الطبيعية للتخطيط.
And this is an acupuncture note --
وهذه هي مذكرة الوخز بالإبر --
or I.M. Pei's. Some small ones
أو مذكرات "أيوه مينغ بي" (معماري أمريكي من أصل صيني). بعض الشركات الصغيرة --
can make the city better.
إنها يمكن أن تجعل المدينة بصورة أفضل.
The smallest park in New York, the most beautiful:
أو أصغر منتزه في مدينة نيويورك، هو الأكثر جمالاً:
32 meters.
32 مترا.
So, I want just to end saying
لهذا أريد في النهاية القول
that you can always propose new materials -- new sustainable materials --
أنه يمكنك دائما أن تقترح مواد جديدة، مواد مستدامة جديدة،
but keep in mind that we have to work fast
لكن ضع في الاعتبار بأنه يجب علينا أن نعمل بسرعة.
to the end, because we don't have the whole time to plan.
ولتحقيق ذلك، لأنه ليس لدينا الوقت الكافي لوضع خطة.
And I think creativity, innovation is starting.
و أعتقد بأن الإبداع، والإبتكار، هو البداية.
And we cannot have all the answers.
و لا يمكن أن نحصل على جميع الإجابات.
So when you start --
لذا عندما تبدأ --
and we cannot be so prepotent on having all the answers --
و لا يمكننا التفوق بالحصول على جميع الإجابات.
it's important starting and having the contribution from people,
إنها بداية هامة والحصول على المساهمة من الناس،
and they could teach you
ويمكنهم تعليمكم
if you're not in the right track.
إذا لم تكونوا في المسار الصحيح.
At the end, I would like if you can help me to sing the sustainable song.
في النهاية، أريد إذا بإمكانكم مساعدتي لأغني الأغنية المستدامة.
OK?
موافقون؟
Please, allow me just two minutes.
من فضلكم، أسمحوا لي بدقيقتين فقط.
You're going to make the music and the rhythm.
أتعرفون، أنكم ستقومون بأداء الموسيقى والإيقاع.
♫ Toonchi-too! Toonchi-too! Toonchi-too! ♫
♫تونتشي - تو! تونتشي - تو! تونتشي - تو! ♫
♫ It's possible! It's possible! You can do it! You can do it! ♫
♫ إنه من الممكن! إنه من الممكن! يمكنك القيام بذلك! يمكنك القيام بذلك!♫
♫ Use less your car! Make this decision! ♫
♫ استخدم سيارتك قليلا! إتخذ هذا القرار!♫
♫ Avoid carbon emission! It's possible! It's possible! ♫
♫ تجنب إنبعاثات الكربون! إنه من الممكن! إنه من الممكن! ♫
♫ You can do it! You can do it! ♫
♫ يمكنك القيام بذلك! يمكنك القيام بذلك! ♫
♫ Live closer to work! ♫
♫ أسكن بالقرب من مكان العمل! ♫
♫ Work closer to home! Save energy in your home! ♫
♫ أعمل بالقرب من منزلك ! حافظ على الطاقة في منزلك!♫
♫ It's possible! It's possible! You can do it! ♫
♫ إنه من الممكن! إنه من الممكن! يمكنك القيام بذلك! ♫
♫ You can do it! Separate your garbage! ♫
♫ يمكنك القيام بذلك! أفرز قمامتك! ♫
♫ Organic, schmorganic! Save more! Waste less! It's possible! ♫
المواد العضوية، المشروع العضوي! حافظ أكثر! نفايات أقل! يمكنك القيام بذلك! ♫
♫ You can do it! Please, do it now! ♫
♫ يمكنك القيام بذلك! من فضلك قم بذلك -- الآن! ♫
Thank you.
شكرا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)